Hello there travellers and welcome to the
first instalment in the "Getting to grips
with Monero" series.
This video is for those of you who want to
ensure that the software you're downloading
and running is in fact the one that the authors
intended you to receive.
In other words this is for the security conscious
user.
It may seem like a pain at first, but most
of what we're doing here is setup and won't
be required when verifying files in future.
It's also just a good habit to get into and
once you get the hang of it, it's a breeze.
Following these steps before running anything
on your machine will mean you're safer than
if you don't,
but please be aware that this is in a relative
sense.
With these steps you're ensuring that you're
running the software the author intended;
it isn't a way to ensure that what the author
intended is safe.
With that out of the way, let's get on to
the matter at hand, the GNU Privacy Guard
or GPG for short.
GPG is a complete and free implementation
of the OpenPGP standard
that's been in circulation since 1997.
GPG is free software, meaning that it can
be freely used, modified and distributed.
I recommend taking a look at the GNU project
and the Free Software Foundation.
Their webpage, is pretty interesting and you'll
find a lot more free software there.
You can also learn more about the OpenPGP
standard on their wiki page.
All of this is linked in the description.
GPG allows anyone to encrypt and sign their
data and communications.
You'll typically be prompted to carry out
some basic operations when handling Monero-related
software, so we thought it'd be good to have
an easy to follow guide.
If you haven't installed the software for
your operating system already, please go ahead
and do so now.
As with all our videos, you'll find all the
required links and terminal commands in the
description.
Most Linux distributions will have GPG installed
already.
If you find that you don't have it, please
check your package manager and install it
from there.
For Windows users you'll need to install Kleopatra.
Let's start by opening up a terminal or Powershell
window and checking which version of GPG we
have installed.
Don't worry that I'm using Windows, these
steps are relevant to Linux as well.
Feel free to copy and paste along with this
video,
but bare in mind that it's good practice to
double check the content remains unedited.
Let's start by typing `gpg --version` and
pressing enter.
If you're not familiar with using the command
line, please remember, you need to hit 'enter'
after each time that you type a command for
the terminal to read your input.
If you weren't sure if you had it installed,
this is a pretty good test.
This command will print some interesting information,
including:
the version, the licence, the home directory
for GPG and the supported algorithms.
Now we've confirmed that it's installed,
we're going to create our very own set of
shiny new keys.
Keys typically come in pairs, a private key
and a public key.
In simple terms, a private key is used to
prove who you are and a public key is used
to tell other people who you are.
It's a pretty simple system, but has deep
roots in cryptography.
If you're interested in reading a little more
about the fundamentals, check out the link
in the description entitled 'How PGP Works'.
To generate our own set of keys we're going
to use the command `gpg --full-generate-key`,
don't forget to include the hyphens.
First it will ask you what kind of key you'd
like to create.
For the purposes of this video we'll be using
the default option 'RSA', so we'll select
option 1.
Next it will ask you about the level of encryption
you require,
the larger the number the more data is used
to generate the keys.
More data generally means more secure.
We're going to choose 4096 bits as it offers
the highest level of encryption.
We'll then be asked how long we want our keys
to remain valid, this is a personal choice.
As there is no limit to the number of keys
I can generate and because I won't be hosting
my keys publicly, I'm going to choose 0, 'never
expires'.
All keys are assigned user IDs.
They're typically made up of a name, comment
and email address.
For the purposes of this video I'm going to
use the following credentials.
Once we've entered all this information we're
going to type 'o' for 'okay',
but before we hit enter I want to warn those
who like to use password generators:
you're going to need to enter a new password
in the next step.
Once we've entered and confirmed the password,
we're going to generate some entropy, in other
words, move the mouse and bash the keyboard
a bit.
The encryption of your keys is based on the
state of your system, moving the mouse, switching
windows and typing helps create more randomness.
Now that we've generated our very own keypair,
we can use the `--list-keys` flag to verify
it's existence.
--GPG --list-keys
During the creation of ours keys, GPG has
automatically added them to something called
a keyring.
The subject of key rings is a little outside
the scope of this video, however it's important
to know that they may be different and you
can create as many as you like.
We won't be specifying any in this video and
because of that we're going to be working
with the default keyring.
To put everything we've just done into practice
we're going to verify the install files for
the official Monero software.
So let's head over to the official Monero
Github repository and click on the "Releases"
link on the right hand side.
The latest release will be at the top of the
page.
Scroll down to "Official Download Links" and
download the file that suits you best.
For me it's the 64-bit Windows version.
Now that it's downloaded we’ll need two
important pieces of information:
Either a signed copy of the file hashes; or
a signature file ending with '.asc'
and the public key of the person who signed
them.
The first of these is located in the "hashes.txt"
which you'll find via a link on the release
page.
I'm going to right click and "save link as".
Let's open it and take a look at what we've
got here.
Hashes are unique identifiers that are generated
by a hashing algorithm.
These algorithms are generated using information
about the file's contents so we can detect
changes easily and quickly.
In our case, we're interested in making sure
that the hash of the file we've downloaded
matches the hash contained in this file.
If you look at the heading and footer, you'll
notice that this file actually comes in the
form of a signed message.
This is important, because now we can see
if these hashes were signed by someone we
know.
If we take a look just above the signature
we can see that the person who signed it was
a contributor by the name 'binaryfate'.
This leads us on to the second piece of information
we need; Binaryfate's public key.
We can find this via the github page we started
on.
Click on the folder labelled **utils**, then
**gpg_keys**.
Here we can find a list of all the contributors'
public keys.
Click on **binaryfate.asc** and then right-click
**Raw** and save it as an .asc file.
Next, open your file explorer and navigate
to the directory in which you saved these
files.
Ensure that both files are in the same folder.
For me, I've just dumped them in my Downloads folder.
With the file explorer open, 'shift+right-click'
and select ‘open Powershell here’.
If you're a Linux user, you can 'right-click'
and select open terminal here.
Since I'm a Windows 11 user it's a bit different
for me as I just have to right-click and choose
'Open in Windows Terminal.'
In all cases it's a fairly similar process.
At this point we’re interested in taking
a look at the fingerprint of binaryfate's
public key.
Fingerprints are best thought of as summaries
of the key.
We can view this fingerprint with the following
command: `gpg --keyid-format long --with-fingerprint binaryfate.asc`
Fingerprints are a useful way of making sure
that the key you're importing is actually
the one you want.
If you know the person whose key you're trying
to import you can check it with them the old-fashioned
way by just asking if this key belongs to
them, but you'll often find that a fingerprint
will be hosted somewhere on the internet so
you won't need to contact anybody directly.
Please bear in mind, if a web page or repo
has been compromised and the fingerprint and
the public key are located in the same place,
the likelihood is that these were compromised
too, so checking the fingerprint is pretty
much pointless.
However, if the fingerprint and key are hosted
in multiple locations, it's always worth comparing
them to be sure.
In our case, we can find the fingerprint for
binaryfate's public key on the GetMonero site.
Click on the heading "Verify and Import Signing
Key" and scroll down until you find the "Verify
the fingerprint matches" section.
Now we can visually compare that to the one
which is printed in our terminal window.
If you've got a match, great, if not, verify
the web links you used and report your findings
to the community.
Now that we have a little more confidence
in the key we've downloaded we're going to
use the command `gpg --import binaryfate.asc`.
Once again we can use `gpg --list-keys` to
verify that it's been added to our keyring.
This step is in many cases unnecessary and
is more relevant to public keyrings and the
pgp ecosystem as a whole.
It's particularly important for something
called the 'web of trust', which is totally
outside the scope of this video.
However you can learn more about the web of
trust through the p2p foundation.
For us, going through this step means that
you have a more simple log when you verify
signatures in the future.
It's possible to add this level of trust to
the signature you've imported with the `--edit-key`
flag.
In our case we'll use the command `gpg --edit-key`
along with binaryfate's email address to identify
the key.
This command will start up the GPG prompt.
You'll know it's running when you see `gpg>`,
you now have a few options including the ability
to sign it with your own key, type ‘help’
to find out what else you can do.
For now, let’s type 'sign', confirm with
'y' and then enter the password you set up
in the previous step.
Don't worry if you see `failed: Access is
denied`.
This seems to happen every time the password
prompt appears and does not mean the operation
has failed.
If you try to sign the key again you will
be able to confirm whether or not the first
attempt was successful
All done.
Use 'ctrl+c' to exit the gpg prompt.
Everything we've done so far has now given
us the ability to verify the signature in
the text file we downloaded earlier.
The next command we're going to use is `gpg
--verify hashes.txt`.
If you're typing this out yourself, remember
that you can use 'TAB' to autocomplete file names.
Although in this case the file name is short enough that it's not really necessary.
If everything has gone to plan, we should
see a message stating 'Good signature from
"binaryFate "'.
If you don't receive this message, please
be sure to verify the links you used
and report your findings to the community.
Now we can compare the hashes in the text
file to those of the file we downloaded.
If you're using Linux you can use the command
`sha256sum --check hashes.txt`,
then look for the version we downloaded and check to
see if everything is "OK".
If you're using Windows, use the command `Get-Filehash`
and then the name of the file you downloaded.
Manually compare this hash to the one in the
hashes.txt file.
GREAT!
Now we know the software that we have is the
one intended by the person who signed these hashes.
GPG has a lot of interesting features and
gives users the ability to sign, encrypt and
decrypt messages.
The 'hashes.txt' file we used earlier was
signed with GPG by its creator, this also
applies to our contact details on our website
and the scripts for our videos.
Let's have a go at signing our own "clear
text" message.
First create a text file called anything you
like.
Here's one I made earlier.
Then use the command: `gpg --user * --clearsign
message.txt`. Which can be found in the description
The asterisk ( * ) should be replaced by the
name given to the private key you wish to use.
The file name 'message.txt' can be replaced
by the name of whatever file you wish to sign.
If you created multiple key pairs and you're
unsure of your user name, you can use the
command `gpg --list-keys` as we've done previously.
Once the command is finished running you should
have a new file in the working directory.
It should have the same format as your original
file with the suffix ".asc".
It's also possible to encrypt and decrypt
messages.
The most convenient way to share these messages
is using the ACSII armor function.
The following command will create an encrypted
message using the monero-guides private key
Anyone who has our public key, is able to
decrypt this message.
Decrypting these messages is rather simple.
In the next example we're going to encrypt
a message that can be decrypted by only us
at monero-guides: `gpg --user monero-guides
--recipient monero-guides --sign --armor message.txt`.
Watch out for the easter eggs coming up in
the following videos.
There'll be a nice reward for a lucky viewer
who's been paying attention.
To close out this tutorial we'll leave you
with this piece of advice:
PGP relies heavily on trust so you should
be sure that the public key you have in your
keyring is in fact trustworthy.
If it isn't, then you may as well skip everything
in this guide and accept the potential risks
of running an unverified file.
Although everything in this tutorial is optional,
it is best practice and greatly reduces the
capabilities of bad actors to infiltrate your
machine.
The instructions in this video will be relevant
to a lot of our other videos so please make
yourself familiar with GPG.
Anyway, that's it for this instalment, may
your newfound GPG powers bring you peace and
privacy!
~moneroguides